Guide to the New-York Historical Society Public Programs and Education Records 1941-2014 (bulk, 1984-2004) NYHS-RG 23
New-York Historical Society
- Series I. Program Files, 1941-2014 (bulk, 1984-1992); 32.92 Linear feet
  - General Education & Tours Files (4 of 7 boxes), 1985-1992 (Offsite-box 31, Folder 1-81)
    Includes tour and workshop evaluations by participants and by coordinators, volunteer hours (in all departments), reports and statistics (e.g., attendance on tours), schedules (see also box 6 of 7 below), and miscellaneous program correspondence and memos.
  - General Education & Tours Files (5 of 7 boxes), 1985-1992 (Offsite-box 32, Folder 1-91)
    This box includes files concerning the administration of the volunteer program, including files on sources of volunteers, blank application forms, docent meetings and training sessions, memos, the N-YHS "Handbook for Volunteers" (circa 1986), and general administrative matters. The box also holds files of various resources not clearly connected with other more specific matters, much of which was likely general background material for docents and coordinators; these files include laminated images, papers on museum education, general information about N-YHS, and an audiotape and filmstrip(?) of "Trinity Parish in New York."
  - General Education & Tours Files (6 of 7 boxes), 1989-1992 (Offsite-box 33, Folder 1-34)
    This box includes volunteer daily and weekly schedules and group reservation forms completed for each arranged tour. There appear to be two sets of reservation forms, one set holding the original completed at the time the reservation was made and the other filed after the actual tour. This latter set holds additional documentation about the monthly tours, including attendance, evaluations, monies collected, etc.
  - General Education & Tours Files (7 of 7 boxes), 1990-1993 January (Offsite-box 34, Folder 1-25)
    This box holds two sets of the "Special Events/Public Programs Logistics Forms." The first set is the more complete and orderly; it is the copy from the Security Department's files and as such includes all program notification forms sent from any N-YHS unit for 1990-early 1993. (These documents were the only ones from that department in the archive and so were added to this record group). The second set are from the Program and Education files and are in some disorder.
  - Adult Tour Mailings, circa 1990 (Offsite-box 35, Cards -)
    Includes the file of cards with organizational contacts for mailing information on tours.
  - Objects Used by Docents, circa 1990 (Offsite-box 36, Item -)
    Includes fragments of stained glass (Tiffany?), wig, small teapot, feathers, samples of stones (e.g., pyrite, agate, etc.), and laminated reproductions of saloon, hotel, and restaurant licenses.
  - Emerson Prize Winners, 1995 (Offsite-box 37, Folder 1)
    Includes a memo noting that Concord Review's first Emerson Prize would be awarded at a ceremony in the N-YHS Reading Room, the event program, and the special isssue of the Review with the winning essays.
  - Landmarks of New York Project. Speaker Biographies, 1998 May 5-19 (Offsite-box 37, Folder 2)
  - N-YHS 200th Anniversary Celebration Video, 2004-2005 (Offsite-box 37, Folder 3)
    Includes contents of 3-ring binder (disbound) with photocopies of licenses, releases, transcript, and other documents pertinent to the video. A standard and loop version of the video in DVDs is in the folder.
  - Program & Exhibition Publicity Brochures (4 folders), 2005-2014 (Offsite-box 37, Folder 4-7)
- Series II. Teaching Resources, 1970-2009; 3.58 Linear feet
  The series includes resources for teachers that were developed by N-YHS or by other institutions or organizations in collaboration with N-YHS. Some of these resources were prepared as teaching aids that tied-in to particular exhibitions that students would be exposed to. Most were prepared to teach subject areas not necessarily related to specific exhibitions or visits to N-YHS. The earliest resources in the series are in the form of printed manuals. Later resources are larger sets of material that include digital media, oversize reproductions, and other content in addition to print matter. The series holds material found as standalone items in the N-YHS archives as of 2016; it is unlikely that this includes all such resources prepared by N-YHS's Education Department.
  The series is arranged in chronological order.
  - America in Art. John James Audubon: Artist, Scientist, Pioneer, 1970 (Offsite-box 38, Folder 1)
  - Audubon's Birds, 1979 (Offsite-box 38, Folder 2)
  - We the People: Our Living Constitution (4 copies), 1987 (Offsite-box 38, Folder 3)
  - The Bicentennial Connection [U.S. Constitution], 1988 (Offsite-box 38, Folder 4)
  - Imagining the New World: Columbian Iconography (2 copies), 1991 (Offsite-box 38, Folder 5)
    Includes the booklet only from the teacher's packet; see the Program Files series above for other files and material concerning this resource.
  - Seneca Village, circa 1997? (Offsite-box 38, Folder 6)
  - New York City 100, 1998 (Offsite-box 38, Folder 7)
  - America Begins in New York [Immigration] (photocopy), 2000 (Offsite-box 38, Folder 8)
  - Teaching Local History: New York City as a National Model (2 copies), 2000 (Offsite-box 38, Folder 9)
  - Elder Grace: The Nobility of Aging, 2000 (Offsite-box 38, Folder 10)
  - Objects Tell Stories: Learning History Through Object Study (Guide to the Henry Luce III Center for the Study of American Culture) (2 copies), 2000 (Offsite-box 38, Folder 11)
  - Cultures, Commerce & Community [17th Century New Amsterdam] (3 copies), 2002 (Offsite-box 38, Folder 12)
  - Home of the Free: Using Photography to Explore Public Service, 2002 (Offsite-box 38, Folder 13)
  - American Musicals Project. Bloomer Girl, 2001 (Offsite-box 39, Folder 1)
  - American Musicals Project. Showboat. 2nd edition (2 copies), 2001 (Offsite-box 39, Folder 2)
  - American Musicals Project. Paint Your Wagon. 2nd edition (2 copies), 2002 (Offsite-box 39, Folder 3)
  - American Musicals Project. Oklahoma, 2002? (Offsite-box 39, Folder 4)
  - American Musicals Project. Fiorello, 2001 (Offsite-box 39, Folder 5)
  - American Musicals Project. Annie, 2002? (Offsite-box 39, Folder 6)
  - American Musicals Project. World War II, 2004 (Offsite-box 39, Folder 7)
  - American Musicals Project. West Side Story, 2000 (Offsite-box 39, Folder 8)
  - Alexander Hamilton: The Man Who Made Modern America, 2004 (Offsite-box 40, Item 1-2)
    Includes two packages of the materials, one complete with shrink-wrapped contents and one partially shrink-wrapped, with some contents missing.
  - Slavery in New York, 2005 (Offsite-box 41, Item 1-3)
    Includes 3 copies of the binders, one is shrink-wrapped and appears to be complete (with a digital disc), the other two binders are incomplete and missing the disc.
  - New York Divided: Slavery & the Civil War, 2006 (Offsite-box 41, Item 4)
    The binder content is shrink-wrapped, but appears to be missing the digital disc and oversize content.
  - Grant & Lee in War and Peace, 2008 (Offsite-box 39, Folder 9)
  - Lincoln and New York, 2009 (Offsite-box 39, Folder 10)
- Series III. Docent John B. Snook Files, 1995-2005; 1.21 Linear feet (Offsite-box 42, Folder 1-59)
  This series holds the files of John B. Snook (1927-2007), who was a docent at N-YHS beginning in 1995. During the course of his career he had been a professor at Barnard, a pastoral counselor, and director of financial aid at Columbia Law School. This series includes Snook's files on exhibitions, other programs, and general N-YHS matters in support of his work with public programs. The bulk of the files include baseline information about exhibitions (press packets, fliers, labels, wall text, clippings, etc.) that are likely found elsewhere in exhibition, public relations, and other record groups. Nonetheless, some files also hold docent-specific memos and guidance that may not be in other files. Further, the files collectively provide insight into the background materials and other resources available to a docent and that could be used to prepare for gallery tours.
  The files were minimally processed at some point, likely circa 2007, and remain in original folders. They were integrated into this record group in 2016 by project archivist Larry Weimer.
  - Files (1 of 2 boxes), 1995-2005 (Offsite-box 42, Folder 1-59)
  - Files (2 of 2 boxes), 1995-2004 (Offsite-box 43, Folder 1-4)